<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div1 id="pics" type="pics">
	<head>Images</head>
	<!-- bishopics.html -->
	<div2 id="p1">
		<head><name>Bridget Bishop</name> Images</head>
		<figure entity="people/btrial2.jpg" thumb="people/btrial1.jpg" twidth="176" theight="150">

			<figdesc>A scene from the play &quot;Cry Innocent,&quot; performed by the acting
				company History Alive in the Old Town Hall, Salem, Mass., June, 1999. In this scene,
				Bridget Bishop, standing in the dock and wearing shackles, listens defiantly to
				testimony about betwitching a pig delivered by Rebecca Bly, while Judge Hathorne
				gestures to Rebecca's husband (off stage) to keep quiet. Bridget Bishop's arrest and
				trial is re-enacted during the summer tourist season in Salem, three times daily in
				the Old town Hall by Gordon College students</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photo by Benjamin C. Ray, 1999</text>
		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/cbishop2.jpg" thumb="people/cbishop.jpg" twidth="126" theight="160">

			<figdesc>The cover of a tourist brochure that depicts several features of local
				tradition concerning Bridget Bishop. Behind her stands the first church of Salem,
				across from the town water pump. According to a story, recorded by Cotton Mather, .
				&quot;As this woman [Bridget Bishop] was, under a guard, passing by the great
				and spacious meeting-house [church] of Salem, she gave a look towards the house. And
				immediately a demon invisibly entering the meeting-house, Tore down a part of it; so
				that though there were no person to be seen there, yet the people at the noise
				running in, found a Board, which was strongly fastened with several nails,
				transported unto another quarter of the House.&quot; Bishop had been accused of
				witchcraft 13 years earlier in a dispute with a neighbor over her orchard and
				damages caused by her pig, shown at the lower right.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Cover: &quot;Salem Happenings,&quot;
				August, 2001. Artist, Stephen K. Swift </text>
		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/bishop6b.jpg" thumb="people/bishop6a.jpg" twidth="191" theight="160">
			<!-- xref doc="../images/people/bishop6b"><figure entity="people/../images/people/bishop6a"/></xref -->
			<head>&quot;Lusty Bridget Bishop is arrested. She was the first to hang.&quot; </head>

			<figdesc>Wax figure of Bridget Bishop as tavern keeper in Salem Village. Diorama
				display, Salem Wax Museum of Witches and Seafarers, Salem, MA </figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph by Benjamin C. Ray, 2001</text>
		</figure>

	</div2>

	<!-- burroughspics.html -->
	<div2 id="p2">

		<head><name>George Burroughs</name> Images</head>

		<figure entity="people/burroughs2.jpg" thumb="people/burroughs.jpg" twidth="175"
			theight="131">

			<head>&quot;Witchcraft Victims on the Way to the Gallows&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> A scene showing a man and a woman on Gallows Hill. The man may be the Rev.
				George Burroughs, who is shown standing in prayer. The woman may be Martha Carrier,
				who was executed with him on August 19, 1692. Also executed on that day were George
				Jacobs, Sr., John Proctor, Sr., and John Willard. The man on horseback may be the
				Rev. Cotton Mather who attended the executions on this day and encouraged the
				hanging to go forward, even though George Burroughs recited the Lord's Prayer
				perfectly and won the crowd's sympathy.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Boston Herald, May 14, 1930. © Artist F.
				C. Yohan</text>
		</figure>

	</div2>

	<!-- gcoreypics.html -->
	<div2 id="p3">

		<head><name>Giles Corey</name> Images</head>

		<figure entity="people/cw1.jpg" thumb="people/cw2.jpg" twidth="134" theight="195">

			<head>&quot;Father! Father!&quot;</head>

			<figdesc>Illustration of a scene in Mary Wilkins Freeman's play &quot;Giles Corey,
				Yeoman.&quot; (1893) in which a fictional daughter, named Olive Corey, bids
				goodbye to her father before his torture by crushing stones. </figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Giles Cory,
				Yeoman.<!-- xref doc="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/salem/witchcraft/texts/wilkins/harp_index.html"></xref -->
				Volume LXXXVI. December 1892 to May, 1893 : 33. New York: Harper &amp; Brothers,
				Publishers, 1893. Artist: Howard Pyle.</text>


		</figure>



		<figure entity="people/gileslong1.jpg" thumb="people/gileslong2.jpg" twidth="183"
			theight="144">

			<head>&quot;Look! Look! It is the ghost of Robert Goodell.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> Illustration of a scene in Henry Wardsworth Longfellow's play &quot;Giles
				Corey of Salem Farms&quot; in which Mary Warren sees the ghost of a man whom she
				believes Giles Corey killed. Seated next to Giles Corey, who stands in the dock, she
				calls out and points to the ghost. Seventeen years earlier, Giles Corey had in fact
				been accused of murdering a man named Jacob Goodale, a servant in his house, who
				died suddenly. Corey was later acquitted of the charge. It was Thomas Putnam,
				reporting his daughter Ann's vision of Goodale's ghost, who brought to the court's
				attention this old accusation of murder this old accusation of murder in a letter in
				1692 as evidence against Corey.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold"> Source</emph>Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, &quot;Giles Corey
				of Salem Farms,&quot; in
				<!-- xref doc="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/toc/modeng/public/LonCore.html"></xref -->.
				Houghton Mifflin Boston, 1902. Artist John W. Ehninger, 1880, p. 752.</text>

		</figure>


		<figure entity="people/tgc1.jpg" thumb="people/tgc2.jpg" twidth="134" theight="132">

			<head>&quot;Trial of Giles Corey&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> Giles Corey being accused in court by one of the &quot;afflicted&quot;
				girls</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold"> Source</emph> :Giles Corey being accused in court by one of the
				&quot;afflicted&quot; girls. A Popular History of the United States. By
				William Cullen Bryant. Vol. II: New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1878: 459.
				Artist: C. S. Reinhardt.</text>
		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/gcdungeon1.jpg" thumb="people/gcdungeon2.jpg" twidth="131"
			theight="180">

			<figdesc> Diorama showing Giles Corey being crushed with stones.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Witch Dungeon Museum, Salem, Massachusetts.
				Photograph by Benjamin C. Ray, 1999.</text>
		</figure>

	</div2>

	<!-- gjacobspics.html -->
	<div2 id="p4">

		<head><name>George Jacobs</name> Images</head>
		<figure entity="people/mjacobs2.jpg" thumb="people/mjacobs3.jpg" twidth="180" theight="133">

			<head>&quot;Trial of George Jacobs, August 5, 1692.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc>This well-known, dramatic painting by New York artist Thompkins. H. Matteson,
				was painted in 1855. Four years later, it was presented to the Peabody Essex Museum
				in Salem by local businessmen Messrs. Ripley and Charles A. Ropes. </figdesc>

			<!-- xref doc="gjacobspics2.html"></xref -->
		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/mjacobs1.jpg" thumb="people/mjacobs1.jpg" twidth="180" theight="133">

			<head>&quot;Trial of George Jacobs, August 5, 1692.&quot; </head>

			<figdesc><emph rend="bold">(Detail)</emph><br/>
				<emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Oil painting. © Peabody and Essex Museum,
				used with permission.</figdesc>
			<text>The painting depicts the trial of George Jacobs, Sr. at the Court of Oyer and
				Terminer in Salem. The scene is an imaginary one, as no records of the actual trial
				exist, and it its not known who was present at Jacobs' trial on August 5th. The
				inspiration for the painting comes from two moving documents written by 17year-old
				Margaret Jacobs: &quot;Margaret Jacobs to her Father&quot; and
				&quot;Recantation of Margaret Jacobs.&quot; See
				<!-- xref="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/etcbin/toccer-salem?id=BoySal2&data=/texts/english/salem&tag=public&part=24&division=div1">Salem 
        Witchcraft Papers Volume 2, Case 24</xref --></text>

			<text>In addition to the officials of the court, Matteson portrays several members of
				the George Jacobs family who became caught up in the witchcraft accusations in Salem
				Village. Kneeling in the foreground is the white haired, 72 year-old George Jacobs,
				Sr., wearing an expensive red cape, with his walking stick lying next to him on the
				floor. At the center of the picture, pointing her finger directly at Jacobs, is his
				granddaughter Margaret Jacobs. Urged to confess to witchcraft to save her life, she
				accused her grandfather among others who had already been accused. The distraught
				figure lunging towards Margaret is her mother Rebecca Jacobs, who was said to have
				been mentally deranged at the time. She, too, was accused of witchcraft. Standing
				next to George Jacobs, Sr. is his son, George Jacobs, Jr., whom Matteson shows
				responding in horror to his daughter's accusation of her grandfather. In the
				foreground, Matteson places a young man and a girl suffering from
				&quot;fits,&quot; caused by George Jacobs senior's invisible
				&quot;specter.&quot; The girl is possibly Sarah Churchill, Jacobs' household
				servant, or perhaps Ann Putnam, both of whom repeatedly testified that Jacobs'
				specter attacked them. <lb/> The black robed magistrates are shown at the bench,
				with the chief magistrate, William Stoughton, towing over the commotion caused by
				Margaret's accusation of her grandfather. One of the magistrates, perhaps John
				Hathorne, who often took the lead role in interrogating the accused in court, holds
				a written document, in front of the young Margaret Jacobs. This document may be
				intended to represent Margaret's written confession in which she accuses her
				grandfather. Judge Hathorne gestures towards the clerk of the court, Stephen Sewall,
				who is shown writing down Margaret's testimony at the clerk's table, with the other
				court records lying in front of him . In the background against the windows Matteson
				shows a group of people who may represent the grand jury. The artist also depicts
				the large crowd of onlookers that typically attended the trials in Salem. </text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/gjacobsgrave2.jpg" thumb="people/gjacobsgrave.jpg" twidth="134"
			theight="194">

			<figdesc> Gravestone of George Jacobs, Sr. placed in the cemetery of the Rebecca Nurse
				Homestead, 1992. The remains of a man believed to be George Jacobs, Sr. were
				recovered from the Jacobs property in the 1950s and finally laid to rest Sunday,
				August 2, 1992, 300 years after he was hanged on Gallows Hill.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph by Richard B. Trask.</text>

		</figure>


	</div2>

	<!-- johnhathpics.html -->
	<div2 id="p5">

		<head><name>John Hathorne</name> Images</head>

		<figure entity="people/jhathorngrv.jpg" thumb="people/jhathorngrv2.jpg" twidth="180"
			theight="145">

			<figdesc> Gravestone of Col. John Hathorne, located in the Old Burial Ground, Salem,
				Massachusetts. Hathorne served as a magistrate on the Court of Oyer and Terminer,
				the special witch trials court in Salem. He was the most active interrogator of the
				defendants in court. The stone reads: &quot;Here lyes interd ye Body of Col John
				Hathorne, Esqr Aged 76 years who died May 10, 1717.&quot;</figdesc>


			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph by Benjamin C. Ray, 1999</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/jhathlong1.jpg" thumb="people/jhathlong2.jpg" twidth="200"
			theight="158">

			<head>&quot;Oh, give me leave to pray!&quot;</head>

			<figdesc>This scene, set in the Salem Village meeting house, shows Judge John Hathorne
				and the Rev. Cotton Mather interrogating Martha Corey, who stands in the dock with
				her hands raised in prayer, with Mary Walcott, her accuser, sitting in a
				chair.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Henry Wadsworth Longfellow,
				&quot;<!-- xref doc="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/toc/modeng/public/LonCore.html"></xref -->,&quot;
				in The Poetical Works of Longfellow. Houghton Mifflin Boston, 1902. Artist, S. S.
				Kilburn, 1880, p. 747. </text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/jhathwax2.jpg" thumb="people/jhathwax1.jpg" twidth="168" theight="160">

			<figdesc> Wax figure of magistrate John Hathorne outside the Salem Wax Museum of Witches
				and Seafarers. </figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph by Benjamin C. Ray, 1999</text>
		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/jhathwax3.jpg" thumb="people/jhathwax4.jpg" twidth="200"
			theight="150">

			<figdesc> Wax figure of magistrate John Hathorne appears to beckon to tourists as they
				enter the Salem Wax Museum of Witches and Seafarers. </figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph by Benjamin C. Ray, 2001.</text>

		</figure>

	</div2>

	<!-- martinpics.html -->
	<div2 id="p6">

		<head><name>Susannah Martin</name> Images</head>
		<figure entity="people/smartin2whit.jpg"  thumb="people/smartin2whit.gif" twidth="621" theight="90">

			<head>&quot;Who turned, in Salem's dreary jail,/Her worn old bible o'er and
				o'er.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc>Susannah Martin portrayed reading her Bible in the Salem jail.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Mabel
				Martin:<!-- xref doc="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/toc/modeng/public/WhiMabe.html"></xref -->.
				By John Greenleaf Whittier, Boston: Houghton, Mifflen &amp; Co. 1876, p. 43.
				Artist, Mary A. Hallock. </text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/smartinwhit.jpg" thumb="people/smartin2whit.gif" twidth="161"
			theight="180">

			<head>&quot;Curious thousands thronged to see/Her mother at the
				gallows-tree.&quot;</head>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Mabel Martin:
				<!-- xref doc="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/toc/modeng/public/WhiMabe.html"></xref -->.
				By John Greenleaf Whittier, Boston: Houghton, Mifflen &amp; Co. 1876, p. 36.
				Artist, Mary A. Hallock. </text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/martinrck.jpg" thumb="people/martinrck.gif" twidth="191"
			theight="180">

			<figdesc> Marker stone at location of Susannah Martin's house in Amesbury,
				Massachusetts.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> A Guide to the Salem Witchcraft Hysteria of 1692.
				By David C. Brown. 1984, p. 45.</text>
		</figure>

	</div2>

	<!-- nursepics.html -->
	<div2 id="p7">

		<head><name>Rebecca Nurse</name> Images</head>
		<figure entity="people/nursecourt1.jpg" thumb="people/nursecourt1.gif" twidth="116"
			theight="150">

			<head>&quot;The sheriff brought the witch up the broad aisle, her chains clanking as
				she stepped.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> This drawing illustrates a scene in John Musick's book The Witch of Salem in
				which Rebecca Nurse is brought in chains to the meeting house where the Rev.
				Nicholas Noyes pronounces her excommunication before the congregation.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> The Witch of Salem or Credulity Run Mad. By John
				R. Musick. New York: Funk &amp; Wagnalls Company, 1893: 275. Artist: F. A.
				Carter.</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/nursetrial.jpg" thumb="people/nursetrial.gif" twidth="160"
			theight="134">

			<head>&quot;Trial of Rebecca Nurse&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> Diorama depicting the trial of Rebecca Nurse, shown seated in the dock at the
				right, the magistrates in the center, and the &quot;afflicted&quot; girls at
				the left.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> 35mm slide © Salem Witch Museum,
				1999.</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/townesister1.jpg" thumb="people/townesister1.gif" twidth="141"
			theight="150">

			<head>&quot;The Towne Sisters&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> Plaster statue depicting Rebecca Towne Nurse, Mary Towne Esty, and Sarah Towne
				Cloyse, wearing shackles. The statue is located in the Salem Wax Museum of Witches
				and Seafarers, Salem. Artist: Yiannis Stefinarkis, ca. 1970.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph by Benjamin C. Ray, 2001.</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/threesov.jpg" thumb="people/threesov.gif" twidth="108" theight="150">

			<figdesc> Photograph of Vanessa Redgrave (center), as Sarah Cloyce; Phyllis Thaxter
				(right), as Rebecca Nurse; and Kim Hunter (left), as Mary Easty.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Video Cassette cover. Three sovereigns for Sarah.
				Videorecording. Night Owl Productions. Producer, writer, Victor Pisano. Director,
				Philip Leacock. Publication info: Alexandria, VA : PBS Video, [1990].</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/nursehse2.jpg" thumb="people/nursehse1.jpg" twidth="170"
			theight="149">

			<figdesc> Rebecca Nurse Homestead, Danvers, Massachusetts.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph by Benjamin C. Ray, 2001.</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/nursemem2.jpg" thumb="people/nursemem2.gif" twidth="135"
			theight="180">

			<figdesc> Rebecca Nurse Memorial, erected 1885. Located in the Rebecca Nurse Homestead
				cemetery, Danvers, Massachusetts. The inscription on the monument reads: Rebecca
				Nurse, Yarmouth, England 1621. Salem, Mass., 1692. &quot;O Christian Martyr/who
				for Truth could die/When all about thee/owned the hideous lie!/The world
				redeemed/from Superstition's sway/Is breathing freer for thy sake today.&quot;
				From the poem &quot;Christian Martyr,&quot; by John Greenleaf
				Whittier.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph by Benjamin C.. Ray, 2001</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/nurse1885.jpg" thumb="people/nurse1885.gif" twidth="170"
			theight="135">

			<figdesc> Nurse Family Association, dedication of the Rebecca Nurse Memorial, erected
				July, 1885. The tall granite memorial is located in the cemetery of Rebecca Nurse
				Homestead, Danvers, Massachusetts</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph, courtesy of the Danvers Archive
				Collection.</text>

		</figure>

	</div2>

	<!-- phipspics.html -->
	<div2 id="p8">

		<head><name>William Phips</name> Images</head>

		<figure entity="people/phips2.jpg" twidth="130" theight="175" thumb="people/phips2.gif">

			<figdesc> Portrait of Sir William Phips. Oil painting by Thomas Child, Boston, ca.
				1687-94.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Cover illustration. The New England Knight: Sir
				William Phips, 1651-1695. By Emerson W. Baker and John G. Reid. University of
				Toronto Press, 1998. Photograph by Nicholas Dean, courtesy of the Gardiner
				family.</text>
		</figure>

	</div2>

	<!-- sewallpics.html -->
	<div2 id="p9">

		<head><name>Samuel Sewall</name> Images</head>

		<figure entity="people/sewallportr.gif" thumb="people/sewallportr.gif" twidth="138"
			theight="150">

			<figdesc> Digital image from an oil painting by Smibert, Museum of Fine Arts,
				Boston.</figdesc>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/sewallmural.jpg" thumb="people/sewallmural.gif" twidth="182"
			theight="150">

			<head>&quot;Dawn of Tolerance in Massachusetts. Public Repentance of Judge Samuel
				Sewall for his Action in the witchcraft trials.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> In this mural size painting Samuel Sewall is shown standing in his pew, head
				bowed, in the South-Meeting House of Boston while the Rev. Samuel Willard, reads
				aloud Sewall's statement of repentance for his role as a judge during the witch
				trials of 1692. The mural is one of five paintings that depict important events in
				the early history of Massachusetts, under the theme &quot;Milestones on the Road
				to Freedom in Massachusetts.&quot; The five paintings hang in the House of
				Representatives, State House, Boston. Artist, Albert Herter, 1942. </figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Pamphlet, &quot;Milestones on the Road to
				Freedom in Massachusetts: Ceremonies at the Presentation,&quot; January 18,
				1943.p. 10. </text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/hserep.jpg" thumb="people/hserep.gif" twidth="182" theight="150">

			<figdesc> Five murals in the House of Representatives, State House, Boston, illustrating
				the theme &quot;Milestones on the Road to Freedom in
				Massachusetts.&quot;</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Pamphlet, &quot;Milestones on the Road to
				Freedom in Massachusetts: Ceremonies at the Presentation,&quot; January 18,
				1943.</text>

		</figure>

	</div2>

	<!-- sparrispics.html -->
	<div2 id="p10">

		<head><name>Rev. Samuel Parris</name> Images</head>

		<figure entity="people/parris.jpg" thumb="people/parris.jpg" twidth="336" theight="499">
			<figdesc>A detailed view of the miniature portrait of the Rev. Samuel Parris.</figdesc>
			<text>Massachusetts Historical Society.</text>


		</figure>


	</div2>

	<!-- titubapics.html -->
	<div2 id="p11">

		<head><name>Tituba</name> Images</head>
		<figure entity="people/tituba.jpg" thumb="people/tituba.gif" twidth="203" theight="130">

			<head>&quot;Tituba Teaching the First Act of Witchcraft.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> Shows Tituba in the household of the Rev. Samuel Parris with Betty Parris,
				Abigail Williams, and other children looking on.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Witchcraft Illustrated, by Henrietta D. Kimball,
				Geo. A. Kimball, Publisher, Boston, 1892. Artist unknown</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/tituba1.jpg" thumb="people/tituba1.gif" twidth="183" theight="160">

			<head>&quot;I am Tituba the Witch.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> Scene in Longfellow's play &quot;Giles Corey of Salem Farms&quot;
				showing Rev. Cotton Mather encountering Tituba in the woods, as Mather travels to
				Salem Village to investigate the witchcraft accusations.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Henry Wadsworth Longfellow,
				&quot;<!-- xref doc="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/toc/modeng/public/LonCore.html"></xref -->,&quot;
				in The Poetical Works of Longfellow. Houghton Mifflin Boston, 1902. Artist John W.
				Ehninger, 1880, p. 723. </text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/tituba2.jpg" thumb="people/tituba2.gif" twidth="200" theight="147">

			<head>&quot;Look into this Glass.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> Scene showing Tituba holding up a mirror for Mary Warren and commanding her to
				gaze into it. When she does she sees Tituba's father, said to be an &quot;Obi
				man&quot; in San Salvador, who practices harmful witchcraft upon people by
				melting a wax figure representing the person. Tituba tells Mary &quot;That is
				the way someone is wasting and consuming you.&quot;.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Henry Wadsworth Longfellow,
				&quot;<!-- xref doc="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/toc/modeng/public/LonCore.html"></xref -->,&quot;
				in The Poetical Works of Longfellow. Houghton Mifflin Boston, 1902. Artist John W.
				Ehninger, 1880, p. 727.</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/titubabryant.jpg" thumb="people/titubabryant.gif" twidth="196"
			theight="179">

			<head>&quot;Tituba and the Children.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> Scene showing Tituba performing acts of sorcery acts for Betty Parris,
				Abigrail Williams, and other children in the kitchen of the Rev. Samuel Parris
				household.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> A Popular History of the United States. Vol. 2. By
				William Cullen Bryant, New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1878, p. 457. Artist A.
				Fredericks</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/titubaswmus1.jpg" thumb="people/titubaswmus1.gif" twidth="225"
			theight="141">

			<head>&quot;Tituba, the accused witch, telling the children of Salem Village
				mysterious tales of the Devil.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> This postcard shows one of the dioramas in the Salem Witch Museum. It depicts
				the scene of Betty Parris and Betty Williams in the kitchen of the Rev. Samuel
				Parris house, listening to Tituba.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Postcard -- Salem Witch Museum. © Salem
				witch Museum (1999)</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/titubawxmus.jpg" thumb="people/titubawxmus.gif" twidth="200"
			theight="150">

			<head>&quot;Tituba, the Witch! Tituba, accused of witchcraft, waits outside while
				the afflicted girls make their accusations.&quot;</head>

			<figdesc> Wax figures in a diorama titled &quot;Tituba, the Witch!&quot; at the
				Salem Wax Museum of Witches and Seafarers, Salem</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photo by Benjamin Ray, 2001.</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/titubatrial3.jpg" thumb="people/titubatrial3.gif" twidth="162"
			theight="180">

			<figdesc> Diorama in which Tituba is on trial at The Witch History Museum, Salem. Tituba
				is shown holding a wax doll, or &quot;poppet,&quot; that Puritans believed
				was used to cause harm to the person represented by the image.</figdesc>


			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph by Benjamin Ray, 2001</text>

		</figure>

		<figure entity="people/titubawtchhist2.jpg" thumb="people/titubawtchhist2.gif" twidth="185"
			theight="179">

			<figdesc> Diorama in The Witch History Museum, Salem. Tituba is shown with her husband,
				John Indian, Betty Parris, and Abigail Williams in the kitchen of the Rev. Samuel
				Parris household.</figdesc>

			<text><emph rend="bold">Source</emph> Photograph by Benjamin Ray, 2001</text>
		</figure>

	</div2>

</div1>
