<?xml version="1.0"?>
<div1 id="minibios" type="minibios">
<div2 id="mb1">
<head><name>Bridget Bishop</name></head>
<p> Bridget Bishop was the first person to be executed during the 
  Salem witchcraft trials. In Salem folklore, she is portrayed as a feisty, fun-loving, 
  lusty, innkeeper who can't seem to keep herself out of trouble. Recently, historians 
  have painted a somewhat different picture, owing to the confusion with Sarah 
  Bishop who also appears in the court records of the witch trials. Indisputably, 
  the Bridget Bishop who was tried and hanged possessed a quick wit and independent 
  spirit that could not be crushed by the court of Oyer and Terminer. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb2">
<head><name>Thomas Brattle</name></head>
<p>Thomas Brattle (1658 - 1713) was a well-educated and prosperous 
    Boston merchant who served as treasurer of Harvard College, and was a member 
    of the intellectually elite Royal Society. In early October 1692 he wrote 
    a letter to an English clergyman which was critical of the Salem witch trials. 
    The letter was circulated widely in Boston at the time, and it continues to 
    be studied for its reasoned attack on the witchcraft trials in Salem. Brattle 
    presents a compelling argument against the legal premises and procedures involved 
    in the afflictions, accusations, and executions, with a particular focus on 
    the validity of spectral evidence in proceedings. He was careful not to argue 
    against the motives of the "Salem Gentlemen" as he calls the judges and ministers 
    at the helm, but rather against the methods they employed. He concludes by 
    saying "I am afraid that ages will not wear off that reproach and those stains 
    which these things will leave behind them upon out land."
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb3">
<head><name>George Burroughs</name></head>
<p>George Burroughs was the only Puritan minister indicted and executed 
  in Salem in 1692. He served as minister of Salem Village from 1680 until he 
  left in 1683. As one of the succession of three ministers who left the Village 
  in the years leading up to the trials, he became involved in the Village's social 
  conflicts. During his stay in Salem he borrowed money from the Putnam family 
  and when he was unable to pay it back, conflict with the Putnams arose. It was 
  at this point that he left. Although he eventually repaid his loan, twelve years 
  later, he was charged, arrested and brought back to Salem from Wells, Maine. 
  Many members of the Salem Village and Andover testified against him and called 
  him the &quot;ring leader&quot; of the witches, a virtual priest of the devil. 
  Cotton Mather also took particular interest in the trial because of Burroughs' 
  unorthodox religious beliefs and practices. He was found guilty and executed 
  on August 19, 1692. His hanging was the only one attended by Cotton Mather, 
  who urged the sympathetic crowd against him. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb4">
<head><name>Martha Carrier</name></head>
<p> Calling her a "rampant hag" and the "Queen of Hell," the Reverend 
  Cotton Mather harbored no doubts that Martha Carrier deserved to be executed 
  as a witch during the Salem outbreak on August 19, 1692. The Salem documents 
  themselves, however, reveal that her crime was not witchcraft but an independence 
  of mind and an unsubmissive character. A daughter of one of the founding families 
  of Andover, Martha married a young Welsh servant, Thomas Carrier, in 1674, by 
  whom she had four children. The Salem accusation against Martha came only two 
  years after the selectmen of Andover blamed a smallpox epidemic on her witchcraft. 
  Although historians have blamed her accusation on causes ranging from a conspiracy 
  against Andover's proprietary families to reaction against threats to patriarchal 
  inheritance, her contentious spirit and the earlier charge of witchcraft seem 
  the most plausible explanation. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb5">
<head><name>Cotton Mather</name></head>
<p>Cotton Mather, one of the most famous (and infamous) figures 
    in the history of Puritan New England, was a complex man of great influence 
    upon American history and the discourse that accompanied the Salem witch trials 
    in the years following 1692. As a prominent Bostonian minister, author, and 
    born on Feb. 12th 1663 as the son of the Harvard president Increase Mather, 
    Cotton's reputation as a stalwart believer in the direct influence of the 
    devil upon the physical world through the spiritual realm was already in place 
    by the start of the witch trials. Consulted by three of the five judges, and 
    friends with all of the major authorities involved, Cotton's self-contradicting 
    positions on the use of spectral evidence and the prosecution of the Salem 
    witches heavily swayed the directions of the trial proceedings and the executions. 
    Cotton was also appointed as the somewhat reluctant first historian of the 
    trials, through the commissioning of his book, The Wonders of the Invisible 
    World, that served to justify the trials to the higher powers in the Massachusetts 
    Bay Colony. It was for this book that Cotton found himself spit upon in the 
    streets (and some annals of history) to the day of his death on Feb. 13th 
    1728. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb6">
<head><name>Giles Corey</name></head>
<p>Ann Putnam, Jr., Marcy Lewis, Abigail Williams, Mary Walcott 
    and Elizabeth Hubbard accused Giles Corey of witchcraft in April of 1692. 
    He pleaded "not guilty" but refused to be tried by the court which, in his 
    view, had already determined his guilt, so he stood mute rather "putting himself 
    on the country." He was sentenced to peine forte et dure, even though 
    it was an illegal punishment, and ended up being torturously crushed to death 
    on (or before) September 18, 1692. One of the major factors which made Giles 
    Corey a prime target was not only his relationship with the rest of the community 
    but also his past encounters with the law, including a prior conviction for 
    murder. His chosen means of resistance and dramatic death reveal a strength 
    of character that playwrights, from Longfellow to Arthur Miller, have found 
    irresistible.
  </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb7">
<head><name>Francis Dane</name></head>
<p>Francis Dane was born about 1615 in England and died on February 
  16, 1607 at the age of eighty-one in Andover, Massachusetts. Dane was the elderly 
  senior pastor of Andover and a highly respected leader of the community. In 
  1682, the congregation hired a young Harvard graduate Rev. Thomas Bernard to 
  aid Rev. Dane with his ministerial duties in his old age. There was tension 
  between the two about their salaries, and the two ministers reacted very differently 
  to the witch trials of 1692. Initially, Bernard did much to aid the accusations 
  of witchcraft in Andover, while Dane had more of his family members accused 
  than any other family in 1692. Furthermore, it was Dane's early October petitions 
  to the General Court for pardons, writing against spectral evidence, filing 
  of slander suits, and bold stance against the witchcraft trials that are credited 
  with ending the proceedings in Andover so quickly. Dane is still regarded as 
  the hero of Andover during the Witch Trials of 1692. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb8">
<head><name>Ann Dolliver</name></head>
<p>The deserted wife of William Dolliver of Gloucester and the 
    daughter of respected Salem Town minister the Rev. John Higginson, Ann Higginson 
    Dolliver was arrested for witchcraft on June 6, 1692 but was never convicted. 
    Analysis of her role in the trials has been difficult until the recent discovery 
    of the transcript of her courtroom examination that sheds new light on her 
    case. Scholars also provide various socio-political or gender-based frameworks 
    for understanding the Salem witch trials within which she can be viewed. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb9">
<head><name>Mary Easty</name></head>
<p>The story of Mary Easty, the 58-year-old sister of Rebecca Nurse 
    and Sarah Cloyce from Topsfield usually draws the portrait, now legendary, 
    of a courageous martyr fighting for her innocence. Her case gives insight 
    into the workings of the trials, and her eloquent and legally astute petitions 
    have been said to help bring them to an end.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb10">
<head><name>Philip English</name></head>
<p>Philip English, the most successful merchant in Salem Town, 
    emigrated from Isle of Jersey as Philippe D'Anglois in 1670. He rose out of 
    obscurity to become the largest entrepreneur and ship owner in Salem, and 
    he married into an established Salem merchant family. He and his wife were 
    arrested of witchcraft in late April 1692, but both escaped to New York for 
    the duration of the trials. No attempts were made to bring English back to 
    face trial. During his hiding in New York, English's wealthy estate was pillaged 
    at the hands of Sheriff Corwin, and little restitution was ever made for his 
    losses. 
  </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb11">
<head><name>Elizabeth Parris</name></head>
<p>At nine years old, Elizabeth Parris, daughter of Salem Village 
      minister Rev. Samuel Parris, played a key role in the beginnings of the 
      witchcraft trials. Curious to know her future marital status , Elizabeth, 
      together with her cousin Abigail Williams, cautiously experimented with 
      fortune telling. Her behavior led to the first three accusations of witches. 
      Trying to shield the involvement of his immediate family, the Rev. Samuel 
      Parris, took Abigail from home and placed her in the home of Stephen Sewall 
      in Salem, where she eventually recovered. She could not have predicted that 
      these innocent attempts at predicting the future would lead to the largest 
      and most deadly witch-hunt in American history. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb12">
<head><name>Sarah Good</name></head>
<p>
    Sarah Good was born to a prosperous innkeeper in 1653. However, her father's 
    estate became entangled in litigation leaving Sarah Good in poverty. After 
    the death of her first husband, she married William Good. The Goods lived 
    a life of begging and poverty in Salem Village. Sarah was regarded as an unsavory 
    person and has come to be regarded through literature as the stereotypical 
    witch, a disreputable old hag. Good was among the first three women accused 
    of witchcraft in 1692 and was the first to testify. She never confessed guilt, 
    but, like Tituba, she did accuse Sarah Osburne, an act that was credited with 
    validating the witchcraft trials and accusations. Good was hanged as a witch 
    on Tuesday July 19, 1692, but not until after the imprisonment of her six 
    year old child Dorcas, also accused of witchcraft, and the tragic death of 
    her infant in prison. 
  </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb13">
<head><name>George Jacobs, Sr.</name></head>
<p>George Jacobs, Sr. was about 72 years old when he was hanged 
    as a wizard on August 19, 1692, along with three other men and one woman -- 
    the first time men were executed for witchcraft in Salem. He was accused, 
    among many others, by his granddaughter, Margaret Jacobs who was also accused 
    and imprisoned. Depending on scholarly opinion, he has been seen as the victim 
    of personal grudges, the casualty of the socio-political climate of Salem, 
    or the target of cultural system's effects on young, socially subordinate 
    women. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb14">
<head><name>John Hathorne</name></head>
<p>Born into a well-established Salem family on August 5, 1641, 
    John Hathorne became a local Salem magistrate and was chosen by Governor Sir 
    William Phips to be a judge in the Salem Witch Trials. During the trials, 
    Hathorne took on the role of a prosecutor rather than an impartial judge. 
    Hathorne's questioning always began with a presumption of guilt rather than 
    innocence, and he appeared to be on the side of the accusers. Hathorne altered 
    the tradition of previous witch trials by encouraging those under examination 
    not only to confess to witchcraft but also to name others who might be witches 
    - a move that accelerated the number of accusations. He died in Salem on May 
    10, 1717, and was later a prominent target of criticism by his own great-grandson, 
    Nathaniel Hawthorne. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb15">
<head><name>Elizabeth Hubbard</name></head>
<p>Elizabeth Hubbard was seventeen in the spring of 1692 when she 
    and three other girls started accusing people of witchcraft. Like many of 
    the other "afflicted" girls in Salem Village, she was an orphan and lived 
    with her great-aunt and uncle, Dr. William Giggs. Elizabeth played an active 
    role throughout the trials as one of the leading accusers. Her afflictions, 
    fits, trances and testimony all contributed to the conviction and execution 
    of many of the nineteen executed innocent people.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb16">
<head><name>Increase Mather</name></head>
<p>INCREASE MATHER (1639-1723): Mather, an influential Boston minister 
    and father of Cotton Mather, is credited with being a force for moderation 
    throughout the Salem witchcraft trials and helping bring them to an end with 
    the circulation of his Cases of Conscience on October 3, 1692. Increase Mather 
    has drawn fire from some historians of the period for his hesitancy to take 
    a firm stand against the trials and executions early in the summer of 1692. 
    However, Mather's unique role as leading minister, President of Harvard College, 
    and confidant of Governor William Phips placed him in the precarious position 
    of contesting the witchcraft trials while supporting the judges. While his 
    actions in 1692 were often self-contradictory, he was, according to Kenneth 
    Murdock regarded as "an ally and leader of those whom we see as the most liberal 
    of his time." </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb17">
<head><name>Susannah Martin</name></head>
<p>The sixty-seven year old widow Susannah Martin of Amesbury was 
    hanged as a witch on July 19, 1692 on the basis of the testimony of the accusing 
    circle of girls of Salem Village and other neighbors. Although she maintained 
    her innocence to the end, a previous history of witchcraft accusations and 
    the momentum of Salem's accusations carried her to the gallows. Martin figures 
    in historian Carol Karlsen's account of the Salem outbreak as an example of 
    a woman who was easily targeted as a threat to the orderly transmission of 
    property down the paternal line because of Martin's role in an ongoing court 
    dispute over her father's will. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb18">
<head><name>Margaret Jacobs</name></head>
<p>Although she was only seventeen at the time of the Salem Witch Trials, Margaret 
Jacobs knew that the safest way out of the witchcraft accusations directed at 
her was through confession. She employed this equation in her initial accusations 
against former minister of Salem Village, George Burroughs, and the patriarch 
of the Jacobs family, her own grandfather, George Jacobs, Sr. Although her accusations, 
among others, led to the execution of both men, it is not her accusations that 
make her case of interest. It is her eventual retraction of these accusations 
and voicing of her own conscience that make Jacobs an icon of strength and integrity. 
While other accusers escaped death by relentlessly accusing one person after another, 
Margaret Jacobs sat in jail facing death for her refusal to stand by her initial 
accusations and confession of witchcraft.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb19">
<head><name>Mercy Lewis</name></head>
<p>Born in Falmouth, Maine in 1675, Mercy Lewis lost both her parents to Indian attacks 
and became an orphan at a young age. Dislocated from her family, like many of 
the accusing girls in Salem Village, she resided first with Reverend George Burroughs 
as a servant and then later with the family of Thomas Putnam to whom she was distantly 
related. As a friend of Ann Putnam and the other girls involved in the witchcraft 
accusations, Mercy herself became one of the most consistent and vocal accusers 
during the 1692 witchcraft trials in Salem.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb20">
<head><name>Mary Walcott</name></head>
<p>Mary Walcott, the daughter of Jonathan Walcott, commander of the Village militia 
and the brother-in-law of Thomas Putnam, was a key accuser in the Salem Witch 
Trials. Walcott was closely related to the Thomas Putnam family; her aunt was 
Ann Putnam,Sr. and her cousin was Ann Putnam, Jr. Although Mary Walcott was one 
of the circle of accusing girls, by the end of the trials she had attracted sixteen 
spectral torturers.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb21">
<head><name>Rebecca Nurse</name></head>
<p>Rebecca Nurse was an elderly and respected member of the Salem Village community. 
She was accused of witchcraft by several of the &quot;afflicted&quot; girls in 
the Village in March of 1692. Although a large number of friends, neighbors and 
family members wrote petitions testifying to her innocence, she was tried for 
acts of witchcraft in June, 1692. The jury first returned a &quot;not guilty&quot; 
verdict, but was told to reconsider, and then brought in a verdict of &quot;guilty.&quot; 
Governor Phips pardoned her, but was later persuaded to reverse his decision by 
several men from Salem. She was excommunicated from the Salem church and hanged 
on July 19, 1692. Her house in Danvers, the former Salem village, still stands 
and is open to visitors. A large monument also marks her grave in the Nurse family 
cemetery on the grounds. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb22">
<head><name>Sarah Osborne</name></head>
<p>In February of 1692, Sarah Osborne became one of the first three 
    victims to be accused of witchcraft in Salem Village. As the widow of Robert 
    Prince-a Salem Villager who purchased a 150-acre farm next to his friend Captain 
    John Putnam's, Osborne was required (by Prince's will) to carry-over their 
    estate to their two young sons. However, by attempting to overtake possession 
    of the property for herself and her new husband, Irish immigrant Alexander 
    Osborne, Sarah Osborne upset social norms that consequently resulted in accusations 
    of witchcraft by the Putnam family. She died in prison on May 10, 1692. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb23">
<head><name>Sir William Phips</name></head>
<p>Sir William Phips was appointed Governor of Massachusetts 
  just prior to the Salem Witchcraft Trials of 1692. Phips created the special witchcraft Court 
  of Oyer and Terminer, and subsequently dismantled it after the Boston ministers 
  and the general public turned against the trials. It is difficult to dismiss 
  the view that he might have stopped the trials sooner had he overseen the court 
  more closely, instead of leaving it entirely in the hands of his zealous deputy 
  Govenor William Stoughton, the chief justice of the court. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb24">
<head><name>Ann Pudeator</name></head>
<p>Executed on Sept. 22, 1692, the widow Ann Greenslit Pudeator 
    was one of the seven unfortunate victims of the final hanging on Gallows Hill 
    during the Salem witch trials. Highlights from her trial included the usual 
    testimony of the circle of accusing girls that Ann had afflicted them in "spectral" 
    form. John Best, Sr. also accused Ann of having murdered his wife, whom Ann 
    had served as a nurse. Mary Warren went to the extreme of implicating Pudeator 
    in the deaths of four people. Historian Carol Karlsen speculates that Pudeator 
    may have been targeted due to her profession as a midwife that placed her 
    in direct competition with male care providers, as well as her defiance of 
    the Puritan female gender ideal of meekness and submission to male authority. 
    Although the details of Ann Pudeator's birth are unknown, it is estimated 
    that she was between 70 and 75 when she was hanged, still protesting her innocence 
    at the hands of false accusations. </p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb25">
<head><name>Samuel Sewall</name></head>
<p>Born in England in 1652, Samuel Sewall moved to America at the age of nine and obtained two degrees from Harvard before marrying into a wealthy family. As a prominent member of the merchant class, Sewall was selected by Governor Phips to sit as a judge for the witchcraft trials on the Court of Oyer and Terminer. Five years after the trials concluded, Sewall issued a public confession demonstrating personal remorse, taking in his words the "Blame and Shame" for his part in condemning innocent people. He was the only judge to do so.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb26">
<head><name>Samuel Wardwell</name></head>
<p>Samuel Wardwell was born on May 16, 1643 to a modest Quaker family in Boston. 
He studied carpentry and moved to Andover, Massachusetts in 1672 to find work. 
There he married his second wife, Sarah Hawkes, a wealthy widow with whom he had 
seven children. In 1692, he was accused of witchcraft and brought to trial in 
Salem. The fact he was found guilty is not surprising, as he had dabbled in fortune 
telling as a young man, had family members who were disliked in Andover, and had 
married a woman whom many did not think he was worthy of marrying. During his 
court examination, he confessed to being a witch by submitting a long and detailed 
story of his indiscretions in order to save his life. His conscience and personal 
courage led him to recant the story and claim innocence, knowing the risk involved. 
He was hanged on September 22, 1692.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb27">
<head><name>Samuel Willard</name></head>
<p>Samuel Willard played an important role in the halting of the Salem witch trials. 
Born in 1640 to a privileged family, Willard had a long simmering devotion to 
the Puritan church, a devotion he would later cultivate at Harvard College. Despite 
his religious fervor, Willard appears to be man of uncommon calm, as he urged 
caution in the accusing and trying of witches. Willard also denounced spectral 
evidence, claiming that the devil could impersonate even the innocent by appearing 
in their shape. After the trials ended, Willard was to push hard for reconciliation 
between the pro-Parris and anti-Parris factions of Salem Village.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb28">
<head><name>Rev. Samuel Parris</name></head>
<p>One of the most notorious personalities in Salem, the Rev. Samuel Parris represents
to some historians the danger of religious power when wielded by self-centered and deceptive 
individuals. To others, his antipathy towards his opponents
in Salem Village was simply a small factor in the larger picture of the
Salem witch trials.  In either case, the persecution of "witches" began
in his household, and through that point extended deeply into the
American psyche.  One cannot help but question the amount of
responsibility that Parris, who began preaching about the work of the
Devil in his parish well before the first accusations erupted in his household,
holds for the events of 1692.</p>


</div2>

<div2 id="mb29">
<head><name>Tituba</name></head>
<p>Tituba Indian holds one of the most infamous (yet still debated) places in the 
history of the Salem Witchcraft Trials. Tituba was an Indian slave in the service 
of Reverend Samuel Parris, in whose home the diagnosis of witchcraft was first 
made. She was the first accused (along with Sarah Osborne) and was also the first 
to confess. Tituba's confession set a precedent and pattern that would run the 
course of the trials -- accused witches confessed and then became accusers themselves, 
thereby validating the previous accusations and the need for continuing investigations 
and trials, as the court desired. Though Tituba was not executed for her participation 
as a &quot;detestable Witch,&quot; she was forced to languish in jail for thirteen 
months after Parris refused to pay her imprisonment costs. She was finally freed 
from jail when an unknown person redeemed her jail fees and took her from the 
Village. Nothing is known about her life beyond Salem Village.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb30">
<head><name>Mary Warren</name></head>
<p>Born twenty years before the Salem Witch Trials began, Mary 
    Warren became one of the most rigorous accusers -- and also a defender and 
    confessor, a unique role among the accusing girls of Salem Village. As the 
    servant of John and Elizabeth Procter, opponents of the trials who thought 
    that the accusers should be punished, Mary encountered much resistance from 
    the two regarding her participation in the trials. Most significantly, Warren 
    introduced the possibility of fraud on the part of the accusing girls when 
    she stated that they "did but dissemble." Arthur Miller's play The Crucible 
    focuses on this unique aspect of Mary Warren's behavior. After her own confession, 
    Warren more actively participated in the accusations, including those against 
    the Procters. She was released from jail in June, 1692.</p>
      
</div2>
<div2 id="mb31">
<head><name>John Proctor</name></head>
<p>John Proctor was an elderly man of 60 years of age when accused, tried,
and hanged for practicing witchcraft in 1692.  Maintaining his innocence
until death, he challenged the court to reexamine the validity of
spectral evidence.  Though it did not save him, his legacy is remembered
in Arthur Miller's play The Crucible.  Though not an historically
accurate depiction, The Crucible does bring attention to the story of
John Proctor and his struggle as an innocent man.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb32">
<head><name>Ann Putnam, Jr.</name></head>
<p>Ann Putnam, Jr. played a crucial role in the witchcraft trials of 1692. 
She was twelve years old at the time, and she was one of the first to
join Betty Parris and Abigail Williams as an "afflicted child".  Though
she is easily despised for her role as one of the most persistent
accusers in the trials, it is important to view her in the context of
her socially prominent family.  Her mother was also afflicted, and her
father and many other Putnams gave testimony against the accused during
the trials.  When attempting to make a judgment on Ann, it is important
to remember that she was very young and impressionable and thus easily
influenced by her parents and other adults.  Fourteen years later she
admitted that she had lied, deluded by the Devil.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb33">
<head><name>Abigail Williams</name></head>
<p>Abigail Williams was one of the main accusers in the Salem Witch trials.
 The 11-year-old niece of Reverend Samuel Parris showed signs of fits
and hysterics in mid-January 1692.  She and her 9-year-old cousin Betty
were the first two afflicted girls in Salem Village.  Abigail gave
formal testimony at 7 cases, and she was involved in as many as 17
capital cases.</p>

</div2>
<div2 id="mb34">
<head><name>John Willard</name></head>

<p>John Willard was accused of witchcraft at the end of April 1692, after
refusing to arrest people that he believed were innocent.  One of his
main accusers was his wife's grandfather, Bray Wilkins, who claimed that
after a mean look from Willard, he became immediately sick.  While
Wilkins' symptoms suggest that he was most likely suffering from kidney
stones, his assumption that he had been bewitched is evidence of the
widespread fear that occurred in Salem during withc trials.  Willard was
hanged on August 19, 1692, maintaining his innocence until his death.</p>

</div2>
<div2 id="mb35">
    <head><name>Martha Cory</name></head>
    
    <p> The accusation of Martha Corey marked a turning point in the Salem witch trials crisis of 1692 in Massachusetts. 
        
        Corey was a newly accepted member of the village church and broke the established mold of only social pariahs being
        
        accused of practicing witchcraft. Major contributing factors to the case being brought against her were an illegitimate son 
        
        born to Corey in the 1670s, and her outspoken criticisms of the trials and the judges involved in the convictions. Although 
        
        Martha espoused her innocence throughout her whole ordeal, she was put to death on September 22, 1692. 
        
    </p>
    
</div2>
<div2 id="mb36">
<head><name>Mary Ireson</name></head>

<p>Mary Ireson is one of the minor characters of the Salem witch trials. 
However, from the one substantive document that has recently surfaced,
we can gain insight into the often-unfair mechanisms of the witch trials
court  - especially how the female accusers' courtroom behavior could
sway a jury, and how petrified the accused "witches" must have been
during their trials.</p>

</div2>
<div2 id="mb37">
<head><name>Mercy Lewis</name></head>

Mercy Lewis Born in Falmouth, Maine in 1675, Mercy Lewis lost both her
parents to Indian attacks and became an orphan at a young age.
Dislocated from her family, like many of the accusing girls in Salem
Village, she resided first as a servant with Reverend George Burroughs
and then later with the family of Thomas Putnam to whom she was
distantly related. As a friend of Ann Putnam and the other girls
involved in the witchcraft accusations, Mercy herself became one of the
most consistent and vocal accusers during the 1692 witchcraft trials in
Salem.

</div2>
<div2 id="mb38">
<head><name>Sarah Churchill</name></head>

<p>Sarah Churchill (or Churchwell), a 25 year-old woman originally from Maine, was both an
accuser and a confessor during the Salem witchcraft crisis.  She is most
noted for the accusations of witchcraft against her abusive employer,
the elderly George Jacobs Sr., and for her admission that her confession
to witchcraft was a pretense to save herself from the gallows -- a
strategy that succeeded.</p>

</div2>
<div2 id="mb39"> 
<head><name>Samuel Parris</name></head> 

<p>One of the most notorious personalities in Salem, the Rev. Samuel Parris represents
to some the danger of religious power when wielded by self-centered and deceptive 
individuals. To others, his antipathy towards his opponents
in Salem Village was simply a small factor in the larger picture of the
Salem witch trials.  In either case, the persecution of "witches" began
in his household, and through that point extended deeply into the
American psyche.  One cannot help but question the amount of
responsibility that Parris, who began preaching about the work of the
Devil in his parish holds for the events of 1692.</p>

</div2>
<div2 id="mb40">
    <head><name></name>William Stoughton</head>
    
    
    
    <p>Lieutenant Governor William Stoughton was appointed Chief Justice of the court
        
        of Oyer and Terminer in 1692.  He ruled over the trials with the
        
        determination to eradicate all witches from Massachusetts Bay Colony -
        
        heavily influenced by his conservative religious  convictions.  When the
        
        court was dissolved, Stoughton continued to enjoy political success and
        
        never apologized for his role in the trials.</p>
    
    
    
</div2>
<div2 id="mb41"> <head><name>Children</name></head> 

<p>The witchcraft crisis in Essex County, Massachusetts in 1692 has long
been known for its unusual list of accused witches. The high proportion
of men accused of witchcraft in the crisis has been noted by historians
for decades, as has the unusual preponderance of wealthy, influential
citizens and upstanding church members. There is one atypical group of
accused, however, who have been largely overlooked. During the course of 
the crisis, at least eight children under the
age of twelve were accused of witchcraft, and most were indicted. This
examination of the eight cases of young children who were accused as
witches will provide a vantage point from which to examine the dynamics
of family and community that shaped the witchcraft crisis.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb42"><head><name>Mary Parker</name></head>

<p>Mary Ayer Parker of Andover came to trial in Salem
Massachusetts, suspected of witchcraft.  During her examination she was
asked, "How long have ye been in the snare of the devil?" She responded,
"I know nothing of it."  Many people confessed under the pressure of the
court of Oyer and Terminer, but she asserted the court had the wrong woman.
"There is another woman of the same name in Andover," she proclaimed. </p>
</div2>
<div2 id="mb43">
<head><name>Margaret Scott</name></head>

<p>The witchcraft accusations and trial of Margaret Scott, executed on
September 22nd, 1692, long have been a mystery to historians.  With the
recently located depositions from her examination, the people, places, and
events associated with Margaret Scott's trial can now be examined and
the mystery surrounding her can be solved. </p>
</div2>
<div2 id="mb44">
<head><name>Gloucester Women</name></head>

<p>Most scholarship on the Salem Witchcraft crisis has focused on Salem
Village and to some extent on Salem Town.  This is hardly surprising, since
the crisis started in Salem Village and these two communities, along
with nearby Andover, produced the vast majority of witchcraft
accusations and trials.  However, other towns in Essex County also
experienced witchcraft allegations, some of which produced trials and
even executions.  One of these towns was Gloucester.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="mb45">
<head><name>John Alden</name></head>

<p>A member of the Boston elite, Captain John Alden was accused on May
28th, 1692 but avoided further proceedings on April 25, 1693
when he escaped from jail and fled to New York where several
high-profile witchcraft defendants were welcomed and protected. Although the
accusers knew him only by name, his profitable connections to Maine and
involvement with the Indian Wars which orphaned several of the accusers
likely contributed to the accusations against him.</p>
</div2>

    <div2 id="mb46">
        <head><name>Thomas Putnam</name></head>

<p>Although Thomas Putnam's role in initiating legal proceedings has been generally recognized as important to the escalation of the witchcraft crisis in Salem in 1692, the immense influence Putnam had on the shape of the trials has not been widely recognized.  Putnam was the father of Ann Putnam Jr., the most prolific accuser in the entire proceedings. Putnam’s importance is generally seen in the fact that he, along with other adults, gave his daughter’s accusations legal weight in first seeking warrants against the accused witches in February, 1692.    Through his work in writing down the depositions of many of the "afflicted" girls in Salem village and his letters of encouragement to the judges, Putnam was one of the major advocates of the trials and sought to exert influence on the proceedings as one of the most prosperous residents and influential church members in Salem Village.</p>
</div2>

    <div2 id="mb47">
        <head><name>Dr. William Griggs</name></head>
        
<p>Dr. William Griggs of Salem Village, though not referred to by name in the court documents, is generally accepted by historians as the doctor who made the diagnosis that the afflictions of the girls in Salem village were caused by “an evil hand,” not by natural causes.  His diagnosis triggered a sequence of events that began with the making of a witch cake and led to hundreds of accusations of witchcraft.</p>
</div2>

</div1>